computer welcome back Gregg it's good to
see you again
and it's why don't you reintroduce
yourself again - sure - it's really good
to chat with you again John I always
enjoy my time and so yeah I'm a
professor of psychology I'm interested
in sort of a meta psychology view and
what things are gonna look like in the
future and all of a sudden it feels like
the future is now you know in a way that
you know it's quite dramatic since when
I last spoke you know I guess the seeds
of that were in the air but I I
certainly wasn't very conscious of them
but there you know lot lots been going
on right yeah I think there's a Chris
master Pietro and I and I sense talk and
I have been talking about you know the
interaction between this as you said we
were talking just before we hit the
record button oh this is probably you
know one of the maybe the biggest event
since World War two and how that sort of
intersecting and interacting with you
know already some existing background
crisis we have a meeting crisis and
other you know socio political and
economic disparity and we see all these
things sort of rolling together in a
really complex fashion Jordan Hall calls
it are unfolding meta-crisis which i
think is apropos and you reached out to
me which i appreciate by the way thank
you and saying you you you have some
thoughts on this and and obviously you
have some relevant expertise and we
talked about that in our our last
meeting together where you you sort of
unpacked in a very precipitations manner
the spirituality implicit and also
needed within a therapeutic context and
but maybe you can you know bring some of
that wisdom to bear right now sure or
some of your thoughts about you know
what does this mean for us how can we
respond to it well yeah I mean I am you
know like everybody I think that's
paying attention I'm experiencing a
significant wave of recalibration and
you know my schema of understanding you
know I certainly like Jordan like
yourself you know have
meta-crisis sense of the globe in the
sense that our relationship with the
planet the complexities of our
arrangements are the way we make sense
out of the world the way we cultivate or
fail to cultivate virtue and character
and wisdom and all of that complexity
was making us very vulnerable yeah to a
wide variety of different you know we we
had stacked fragilities which is
something I think that you know Jordan
Hall would speak about and inter system
dependencies in ways that we don't
understand that make a massive flux you
know in those macro level systems really
vulnerable to lots of externalities and
contingencies that then will create
waves of change that are very very hard
to anticipate and I think that's what
we're seeing and so for me and I think
that you know for all of us then what
will happen is that you'll start to then
get an enormous sense of anxiety and I
think you you and Jordan spoke to this
some in the sense that that anxiety will
then start to look for sense making
systems potentially transfer into fear
and belie and and oh my god this is it
you know and then and then try to attack
certain kinds of things because there's
a general unprecedented
thats a ill stated problem that's hard
to solve right right now and and and
then what to do with that you know and
so one of the things that I would want
folks to think some about is is the
first I talk about awareness acceptance
and change mmm no sort of
developmentally those are big three like
if I do psychotherapy what is the work
of psychotherapy they almost always fall
under one of those three categories
awareness so we want to create a
metacognitive understanding of thoughts
feelings relationships situations
history and and piece them together with
more richness and sophistication and
complexity you know so you want that
that's one of the things that we do and
we all we all want that and so all right
and then as you gain awareness then
there's this dialectic awill
acceptance like how do we how how do we
be with say pain or unpressed a table
anxiety you know distress of of whatever
might be present in our psyche how do we
maintain that from a number of different
perspectives and and also how do we
become through active change you know
and maybe imaginal structures of what we
could be ideals virtues notions symbols
right to become better grow to become
more adaptive and so you know so when I
find myself in this kind of situation
I'll get bumped you know by the wave of
panic say you know I've definitely sort
of my daughter
two nights ago had a really bad migraine
she gets them maybe you know every two
or three times a year
my son ah so we were there and she was
crying you know and and my my wife and I
were there and you know normally you'd
have more psychological resources right
yeah you know but I will tell you you
watching my daughter cry and in this
context had you know had added layers of
meaning right right because you're sort
of like okay there's a there's I think
there's gonna be a wave of suffering I
mean that's not very profound but it it
will be quite intense and when you feel
it in your heart and you get can get a
little overwhelmed so I had to take a
moment to find my centerline you know be
in contact with that recognize what that
means for me and and cultivate a sense
of curiosity with it a capacity to
tolerate it
really enhance my loving compassion for
us as humans my daughter myself right
and then just situate myself as
motivated to what valued outcomes they
are given the situation that I'm in you
know so those that's that's the calm mo
kind of psycho technology that I talked
about before and you know I so I've had
maybe two of those two moments since
this thing started where it really felt
you know because I'm pretty pressed with
all of the things that are going
at least in the way my mind rolls them
out but anyway I'll stop there that's no
I
you don't have to stop I thought it was
excellent yeah I reckon the application
of the comma calm mo and you are you
know I think that's very valuable and
the way you just went through sort of
their concretely what you did in the
face of sort of meant mounting panic
given of course the fact that we're now
all suffering cognitive overload and you
know a sense of scarcity in a sense you
know Chris and I have been talking about
how a lot of you know we're going
through an enforced period of you know
reciprocal narrowing and Dom aside in
which a lot of what we found to be home
and the world is collapsing in and we're
feeling threatened even in our in our
homes and and the meaning of everything
is in question and so you know in that
sense this is magnifying the enactment
of important aspects of the mean crisis
it's exactly right that's exactly right
I mean I just happened to see something
on psychology day a little bit that was
trying to deconstruct some of the key
elements of you die ammonia you know in
terms of purpose coherence of one's life
narrative and then it really hit on
mattering and argument mattering was you
know was he and in this particular
analysis mattering popped even more than
coherence or purpose and yeah you know
yeah you get this whole wave and you
know those of us that are existentially
inclined you know as all you always you
know at some level of it confronted the
existential absurdity and the inherent
fragility of human life in general in
our own human lives you know this is
this is one of those moments at some
level you know where you it is at least
and confronts some of that and and the
struggle to matter and how to make sense
out of mattering in these kinds of
moments as I think what you know what
the human condition often finds itself
as being about it's the point about
mattering is is so directly and
personally relevant that's why I was out
of frame it so AM are flus basically my
tech guru
he said you know one of the things
because I'm sort of like how can I help
and what can I do and we've been talking
about doing this and he said well why
don't we release it now and we'll just
do your put your meditation course
online live straight of it free to
everybody and I was I was surprised by
how much having a concrete sense of
being able to make a difference for
other people and to matter to other
people was actually also you know I
don't know what to say therapeutic for
me that says I could potentially help in
some way I'm not trying to be
presumptuous but you know people are
saying it's helping so I'm going on what
people are saying oh absolutely
right and that you know that comes again
to this whole point of mattering of
being bright not just how things are
relevant to me but how I am relevant to
outside of my and it's interesting how
much I mean I don't like to use the
cliche of the silver lining because it
tends to be too dismissive but a Peter
Peter Lindberg talks about this as being
a Kairos like a turning point because on
one hand we're getting this sort of dama
side reciprocal nearing yes whole world
view all of the all of the complacent
obviousness although one second just one
second sorry I'm sorry I said a little
bit no no and yes go ahead and you know
Peter Lindbergh talked about when a
Kairos because while we're having all
this reciprocal narrowing and Dom aside
as you just said you know mattering and
you know directly connecting to other
people is popping out as a weight that
that thing that I attended to background
a lot is actually foreground thing that
you know I have to rely on that's right
right
this and I were talking about you know
that I actually cannot pause you there
for two seconds I think
so fundamentally actually in terms of
realizing what's relevant yes all right
I put it in realizing what's relevant
your your capacity John to be in a
position to offer the kind of psycho
technologist individuals that they need
at this moment to foster growth you know
what in some ways that's exactly what
that's the essence of what mattering is
about is to socially influence people
towards the growth and meaning processes
that they can enact you know and so it's
so it is something to be honored as
exactly the kind of value and quite
frankly if we think about what's what
the values that we need to embrace on
the other side of this you know on the
other side of the meaning crisis that's
exactly that would be an exemplar right
yeah of the kind of things that need to
matter so I just want to I just want to
hold that and and honor that no thank
you for saying that I think that's right
I think wisdom as both the the reliable
ability to ameliorate you know the way
in which you know these conditions can
lead us into self-deception so that we
have the discernment to see through you
know the way all of this can cloud us on
powerful ways and then the affording of
the reliable affording of the these
connections ultimately are constitutive
of our humanity our sense of our
humanity and our meaning yeah I think
that wisdom is needed more yeah now more
than ever
um and and I I don't want to say that I
I was mentioning to Chris the other day
because we were you know as you know
Greg we're doing this long project on
dialectic and via logos yes and I was
mentioning people forget that the
Platonic dialogues are often set in
Athens the Peloponnesian War literally
under siege and there has literally been
a plague that has literally killed the
leadership Pericles and Socrates is in
that environment and yet he's doing what
he's doing
and so to to put him back into that
context for us or at least as much
we can without being anachronistic I
think his is very apropos the kinds of
things that come to be central when as I
was saying earlier you know the the the
the complacent obvious nests of common
sense or the sense of you know the
unquestioned a sense of technical
mastery we have over things when both of
those so-called certainties are revealed
to be the paper tigers that they are all
right then right the question of wisdom
and meaning becomes central I understand
you know that right now we have to give
priority to survival in some important
ways but in the end I and I think you I
want to turn it back over to you because
you you you sort of says something about
this in the end it's not just sort of
health that's the issue here right
absolutely not I mean its well-being
I mean and it's well it's virtuous
well-being yes yes you die a monic
structures you know of a beam that I
think those of us that care about the
meaning crisis would say that we have
drifted from if we understand ourselves
our relationships to ourselves to each
other I we it in relationship to the
planet and the Harmony we we have not
you know we're caching bad checks you
know yeah right and those externalities
are building and we've lost a bit of our
way in relation and and that is the
great hope that I have for this virus is
that in many ways it's and I want to be
clear I say this as somebody you know
I'm a full professor with tenure and
there are a lot of people that are have
a lot more vulnerabilities than I do so
I know I don't want to say this glibly
because I'm somewhat safe although I
have my children I have my parents I
have lots of people that are actually
potentially going to be vulnerable here
but I really do think that what we need
is some leadership that this holds the
suffering and the pain of this and at
the same time helps without being glib
or trite recognize that there's
opportunities and affordances for wisdom
in this thing
yep deep deep recalibrations I mean this
is probably going to be the best year
ever for the planet in terms of over the
last you know within the last 10 15 20
years in terms of carbon footprint and
things like that as the GDP comes down
there's a lot of things that aren't
being burned and damaged and happening
and there's an enormous opportunity for
us to then potentially shift like I've
been talking about zoom topia you know
I've had more great conversations on
zoom over the last two weeks than I've
had you know and that there's no carbon
footprint there there's lots of good
wonderful connection we thought we
formed certain kinds of communities
seeking those kinds of they feel healthy
so I'm I'm thinking about kind of the
processes by which we hold and attend to
the kinds of events that I you know I
had with my daughter and things like
that and come together and know that
family's going to be stressed and and at
the same time we need leadership we need
guidance we need we need hope we need
movement towards valued states of being
and I really do believe there are in
fact my old mentor and still good
friends sociologist Joe Mikulski I just
put up on my Psychology Today blog you
know the pandemics silver lining
playbook and he narrated after
identifying the yeah after identifying
the dangers and the pain there really is
a lot of potential opportunity here for
growth in an adaptive direction so let's
talk about that because I think that was
very well said well you just you just
said there's definitely that opportunity
there's also a lot of threat you
mentioned that earlier there's a lot of
threat in which people could try and
find you know the the lightning rod to
discharge their fear to try to transform
their fear into anger so that they can
feel that they have a narrative that
gives them some action to perform these
are all real dangers you would know that
better than I in fact I'm sure you see
that kind of transference and
displacement going on within therapeutic
context and it's happened in a clinic
room here and there so you know what I'm
referring to I think there's also a
danger of nostalgia which is let's get
back to nor
as soon as we can and I think that's and
I if this came out in the discussion I
would Jordan Hall I think that's a great
mistake I think thinking that this is
going to be the only pandemic that we're
gonna face in the next 10 years is III
think that I find that highly improbable
I think all the factors that made this
happen are still in place and are going
to ramp up once again if we don't make
significant systemic changes and we
won't have the you know the the economic
leverage to do what we're doing right
now multiple times and we're gonna wear
things down and so I think there's a
danger of nostalgia which is let's get
back to normal and let's just pretend
you know that's never gonna ever happen
again I think that's a threat that we
have to take very seriously because
nostalgia can be very sort of welcoming
in in their earth SATs homecoming that
they sort of give you right and then the
other fear I have is a fear of kind of
utopia in which people use this as an
excuse for claiming justification for
their particular ideological vision or
right because you can see that happening
- you can see people saying aha you know
I told you and you know we and so those
strike me as both very significant
dangerous what are your thoughts about
that oh absolutely
I mean you know the the I mean first off
I I encourage anybody to take a legion
they just put it up over on rebel wisdom
Daniel smarten burgers or risk
assessment analysis from two days ago or
whatever and he's a you know in my
opinion a very very clear systemic
thinker and and so if you if you want to
wonder about whether or not this
systemic interdependencies and certainly
Jordan Hall does this also very well the
systemic independencies that we have
stacked as a system of vulnerability
to that and and whether it's a pandemic
or whether it's a financial crisis or
whether it's a release CRISPR virus you
know biotech technology that somebody
builds or whether it's a particular type
of weapon deployment we there's the
vulnerabilities that we have in
relationship to our systems and their
and their global interdependencies that
are poorly understood yet known to be
intertwined in a particularly vulnerable
and potentially highly fragile way is
why those of us that think big about
these issues know that the the system is
fragile you know if there's a there's a
profound fragility that resides in
relationship to our current system so
those people that want nostalgia you
know my point was be very aware that you
we were living on borrowed time
you know I mean we were living on
borrowed time we were not in a healthy
we were addicted to certain kinds of
things yeah yeah and and what I say you
know and I try not to say this
politically but I I my assessment you
know is we elect President Trump for a
number of different reasons but when
people say that he's authentic one of
the things that they mean about him is
that he represents a particular type of
archetype and I believe he represents a
particular type of archetype that we've
been living off of a shallow
consumeristic kind of narcissistic
me-first egotistical frame of reference
that basically was like that is what we
are and I somebody vote Democratic I'm
also saying I am Trump you know and and
we kind of have to recognize that there
so when I if I were here people say hey
we just got to go back the good times
were good in certain ways but they were
building a nested set of fragilities
that were very very dangerous we were
not anti fragile integrated coherent you
know and and and our inability to
respond to this is just diagnostic of
that and there's other systems that are
gonna be coming and hitting this thing
and we can only take so many we'll see
how this one happens you know we'll see
if this one grows so I think that we
need leadership that says this is a I
hope this will be a somewhat painful but
not catastrophic wake-up call and that
better be a wake-up call to say that we
were addicted to things that
dangerous to be addicted to meaning that
we have gotten into dukkha Paris excite
mind structures that have narrowed our
field of understanding and we need to
use this to wake it up so so and at the
same time the world is changing so much
than anybody has an ideology that thinks
they know what the future is right that
they know what the answers are in terms
of what 2030 2040 should look like
there's great ancient wisdom traditions
and a lot of intelligent thought about
the kind of collective intelligence ease
that we need to bring to bear but those
things are gonna emerge and they're
gonna have to grow from the ground and I
don't think anybody says that they have
a prescribed ideology that has it all
well whatever right Wow very eloquently
said Greg that was really wonderful I
wanted to and thank you for alluding to
some of my work in what you were saying
that I appreciate what you said and I
like the way you you you you pointed how
there's a common thing and and both the
utopianism and the Nostalgia are getting
it wrong which is sort of the emergent
complexity and how much how much
ignorance we have in the face of it I
think that's really really very well
said I wanted to bring up one point that
johannes anita Houser talks about and
kim it's he and guys in stock of had
some I've had one with your harness and
then Joe your harness and guy and I had
one he brings a sort of a Haida garyun
critique and one of the things he's been
talking about recently and it converges
with stuff Chris and I are working on is
how how it's happening right now it has
what it's thrown us back on to the sort
of the god of our world which is our
subjectivity right and you alluded to
that with our narcissism right
and so right we're and we're being sort
of forced now and this is almost like
you know a crooked Guardian moment we
sort of well I am I I'm self made and
it's all you know and so you have that
that you know the intense authority of
our of our subjectivity and now we're
actually being forced to it and the
point is finding that what is supposed
to be the own phallus of the world I am
the center and my subjectivity in the
Cartesian cogito and all that right I'm
finding wow this is actually really
shallow this it doesn't have any of the
depth or resources from which I can give
birth to the wisdom and the growth I
need and we need for it even better in
order to respond appropriately to this
crisis and I think that's I think that's
a very important point that you know
that this challenges that whole
orientation which I think you rightly
point out Trump exemplifies as an
archetype that shallow all-consuming
self referential subjectivity yes I mean
and that's why we're that's why we're
psychically fragile yes you know and and
and so to to then say you know I matter
because I have this degree from you know
from some Ivy League and I matter
because I've climbed the market matter
and I matter because I have a 4,000
square-foot house and I matter and now
all of a sudden you see this wave of
economic collapse in a particular way
right and then you're like wait a minute
I do I do all these toys make me matter
which of course everybody on their
deathbed realized it's not all the toys
you've eliminated that makes you matter
anyway right it's the it's the positive
wise impact that you've had in the world
that ultimately allows the subjectivity
reflect on itself with some degree of
existential stability you know now what
I think is happening given our culture
in its corruptions
is is yeah but this is gonna be an
existential crisis for a lot of people
because that collapse onto subjectivity
is going to realize a shallowness and
this is what the work of the you know
through the coronavirus suffering and
the post coronavirus reality if this was
a wake up call and actually it's sort of
well a very well position to do it
because we're gonna be alone with
ourselves right with lots of time on our
hands and a lots of fiddling about what
matters and so one of the hopes is is
that this can knock a system to waken to
the existential realities that I believe
the psychic is soul into spirit really
requires
to have to have integrity coherence
purpose and mattering so I mean that was
well said and and then the you you of
course and I think you did it very
thoughtfully as you always do you invoke
some you know terms laden with a
spiritual and religious heritage spirit
you know that's broken soul and of
course there's a difference between you
know you know when Descartes thought
that he could capture what we had
previously been meant by the word soul
with with that moment of
self-consciousness I think that was a
breathing pivotable I pivot all that I
may be pitiable
in our cultural cognitive grammar uh but
this brings me to the point that I
wanted to say more explicitly a lot of
people are facing this kind of crisis
let me let me let's do a bit of history
so you mentioned world war two right and
then right after it of course is world
war two part two which is the cold war
right and let you see in America that's
people think of it you know that it's
been the steady decline in for example
church attendance or religious
affiliation but you see after World War
two you see this huge spike right in
religious attendance affiliation right
and so what I mean is people have tended
and and that it's that's just one
example of a long-standing pattern that
when people face these kinds of
civilization worldview dhama side things
they typically have been able to turn to
a religious framework it's dumb
something to take them out of their
subjectivity give them some access to
wisdom literature and you know what I'm
going with this of course which most
people know you know we don't have that
right anymore
and pretending you can't just you trying
to take on a religion you currently
don't have is like trying to say you
have a friend that it's not currently
your friend it just doesn't work right
there just says hey sure yep nope so
there's a sense in which you know large
segments of our population are facing
this not only do they have the
shallowness of consumerist subjectivity
and you know and the fragmentation and
the fragilities of the meaning crisis
attendant upon all of that is of course
they don't have ax
us too religious and wisdom traditions
that can put them in touch with the
resources they need in order to do the
waking up that you're talking about it's
one thing you know to sort of impasse in
the ninth off problem it's also another
thing knowing how to move out of and you
know create a more encompassing framing
that allows you to get unstuck brilliant
there was this guy they put out this 50
lecture series like to become aware of
this process and how we might awaken
from it I don't know you should check it
out it's really good you know so for me
I know we you and I have been wrestling
in parallel with very similar kinds of
dynamics so you know in terms of my
history I'm raised as sort of in the new
atheist tradition of Dawkins and over
the course of my maturity I guess if you
want to use that term not in a
pejorative way but just certainly in my
own thinking especially as a
psychotherapist and then building a
system of understanding that set the
stage for me to transcend what you know
I came to see Ken Wilber calls it the
naturalistic scientific view as sort of
a materialistic flatland a reductive
flatland I've had encounters with people
coming back from you know the first year
of college
oh I realized that I'm just a bunch of
chemicals right it was like you know
that kind of and I had a bit of that you
know and then I've realized over the
period of my own evolution in the system
that I built how unbelievably horribly
misguided that is oh it is profoundly
misguided and there is an opportunity to
develop to an awakening view so so I'll
just go back and then we can fill this
in a number I think there is a way to
develop a religion that's not a
supernatural religion of course to put
put it in those terms that you and
Jordan Hall have been dialoguing a lot
they're really they're really is and I
believe that part of the success of
humanity as we've transitioned over
these next three decades is discovering
precisely that it's covering precisely
how to make sense out of that claim with
coherence and Concilium sand
in a degree of sanity because listen
obviously this naturalistic scientific
frame that we are handed that you know
maybe Aristotle sort of intuited but he
didn't have access to you know the
dualistic certainly a naive concrete
dualistic world for many of us is well
we're not going back there
no but at the same time the idea so when
I use the word soul I'm actually using
it in a pretty close to Aristotle Ian
sense the old term as you know the
psyche it's really the form of your life
at a bio vegetative animal sensory motor
and human rational way right and and and
I want my soul to approach to be a
participant in you die a monic ways of
being you know maximizing well-being and
that point that that sort of absolute
high point is trying to root that's
where my spirit I would say would reach
to so what is the best that I can be you
know in relation so if for example if
you if you're you're working really hard
you're bringing your psycho technologies
of meditation and Buddhist wisdom and
education and pedagogy to a wide variety
of different people that are then can
utilize that for their own growth well
that's it that's a spiritual endeavor as
far as I'm concerned right and that's
that simply means that I value you I see
that as virtuous I look up to it I see
it as something that you know the end
that if we all did you know I think
Jordan Peterson gets this right when he
says you don't have to believe
necessarily in a heaven and a hell in
any supernatural sense you just need to
go to the gulags or go to the
auschwitz-birkenau Locke you know what
my Jewish family it's like there's a big
difference you know and mattering to
have a loving family where people are
respected and held and as opposed to
something horrifying and so those are
very that's what matters and that's what
grounds a value system and if you try to
cultivate your life to live to that and
aspire to what it could be in an
imaginal sense man you know that's
realizing what's relevant
and gives us something to to live for I
was very well said you I'm sorry this
isn't supposed to be a left-handed
compliment you're extremely eloquent
today I've got a lots of Zoom practicing
really well yeah I like the way you sort
of you know that maybe the central task
coming out of this is to in discover in
a in a practicable way I don't say
practical anyway anymore because I
reserve that for what it now denotes
right I want to talk about be you know a
way they can be put into practice what
this religion that's not a religion is
going to look like and help III I think
that getting into these kinds of
discussions so we can marshal the
distributed cognition so that we can
help conduce it into existence because
it's already emerging I think in an
importantly I do see that as one of the
central tasks facing us right now and
I'm hoping that as this community this
biological dialectical community forms
that we will get increasingly better
translating a lot of this theory into
lives into lives and relationships and
you're you I think you will play up a
particularly important role to play in
that precisely because I mean you
already have this overarching the tree
of knowledge and you're doing all this
work on trying to get all these various
levels you know integrated in all use
your your as you given an Aristotelian
fashion which i think is a powerful
model to follow but I think I mean your
particular expertise I mean there's a
sense in which you know the cognitive
the existential the ontological having
to do with your worldview right and the
aspirational you know all come into the
Nexus of the therapeutic situation
you've had to you know so I see
spirituality as having to be what you
know what what
it activates all the kinds of knowing
and activates them across the cognitive
of the existential her ontological right
and then I know that you see you see
something very analogous to this in your
work and and I'm not I'm not trying to
you know background the theory you're
doing but what I'm saying is your
expertise also because like I said the
therapeutic context is you know in some
ways the closest we have right now to
the Socratic encounter now I don't think
it's the same and I think you would
agree with me on that and you know in
one of the work that I'm trying to some
of the work I'm trying to do with you
and especially with Chris and Peter and
guy and Jordan is yeah but how do we
take that you know here's circling out
here and here's here and then how do we
get back to what Socrates was doing with
those things which is also the
philosophy ax the cultivation of wisdom
so I think you have an important role to
say to that well I mean I thank you and
yes I mean either I would you know I've
been doing therapy for what 25 years or
so uh it is a crucible you know it
really is it's a crucible of
encountering I mean people keep coming
to therapy because of some soul spirit
concern and in the generic you know
y'all my life see they're not going very
well
or I'm having an existential collapse
crisis I I can't make sense you know out
of what I am and what I'm doing and I'm
in a panic mode or I'm gonna depress
shut down mode or you know that's that's
that's what it's for
right but what I've actually it's
interesting but you say that because
it's also the case that I'm actually in
this context and maybe over the last two
years or so I'm really frustrated with
what I see is the institutional barriers
that are built up around the
psychotherapy world okay and meaning
like you know it's like so much so that
I've I mean I need to have it but it's
like I want to give up my license and
just go and talk to people about like
the secrets that we built in the therapy
room and then and then we carve them out
is this sort of confessional and then we
have all of this stuff that oh and and
then we do this horrible thing kind of
like the psychopharmacology although
they do it in different ways like Oh
now you have a certain negative level of
negative Afric will you go see an expert
they'll help you figure that out right
we do not want to farm out all of the
psycho technological wisdom to two
secret isolated confidential rooms with
professionals not what we want to do we
want to take that knowledge and we want
to insert that knowledge as clearly and
applicable ec2 to the wisdom of the
dialog in real indigenous human
exchanges I mean that's what we really
want to do yeah right
so I want to connect with you guys and
and connect to bring all of this stuff
out of the therapy of course with
specific you know psychological health
related issues in particular of course
we need a professional context but we
want to generalize that stuff that ya
know yeah and we want to generalize it
too because of course as you know as
much as we can personally reflect it is
the vast majority of our health let's
face it is embedded in the society in
which we live yes yes right so we need
to create a society that is conducive to
wisdom and psychological flourishing
that's that's the responsibility and I
actually I don't know that psychology
especially not with its focus on
individual psychotherapy I don't know
there's been that great in helping you
know in society I think it Cloisters a
lot of stuff away I think it slices a
professional knowledge that shouldn't be
professional I think it should be and
and so I think we have to get out there
and and hand the psycho technologies and
embed them in the communities and the
relationships that we live in right this
is Socrates in the Agora
right Socrates is walking into the
market right right and we need
philosophy we need pedagogy we need
psychology all to come together as part
of society not as siloed separate
isolated things but as real-world around
the day or dinner table realities that
are part of and parcel to the human
experience yeah I agree
I think that's very well said I think
that's very well said
so that brings me again to what do you
think needs to change them
institutionally because you and you sort
of invoked I believe an institutional
prison in some ways in his prison or
oystering or warehousing it like the a
lot of these images came to my mind when
when you you were speaking so
passionately well I didn't have the
language before I sort of entered into
the you know the meta modern community
which I know that you know and learn
things like the blue church from Jordan
Hall and that kind of stuff and I sort
of feel trapped in that in retrospect I
feel trapped in the blue church of
psychology both inside the Academy
inside its psychotherapy and I actually
see it now as they try to follow I'm you
should I think they're opening up of
course because they have to but some
people as they try to follow the rules
of confidentiality and it's state
licensure and because everyone now is
trying to do therapy and now all of a
sudden you're doing everything
telehealth and everyone disperses to
their homes and what is okay and I get
it it's it's complicated but it's just
so out of date it's just so archaic and
just so misguided it's just like the
whole blue church narrative writ large
so in the sense that the institutional
ways of thinking inside let's say inside
the Academy
okay so inside the Academy I kept
bumping up against classic and peeresses
you know with the theory is like sort of
like well show me the data it's like
well okay let's have a conversation
how's that for data then the postmodern
so so what do i what do i hope i hope
that we let the lesson that we learn
from this is that we were in a
vulnerable spot okay i hope that the
people can see that what we need to
transition from is what I would call
late stage capitalism so-so capitalism
did a great thing in turning in many
ways I believe that I'm somewhat of a
human Exceptionalist I believe you know
humans are exceptional and confer value
to them although all sentient beings
aren't that but humans are special and
we did a lot of good things and
pulling all the resources from many of
the resources from the earth and doing
stuff like this look at my house it's
great right but at the same time you
know and I know and everybody thinks
about this issue knows that people
around seven and a half billion people
can't live like you and I I've become
accustomed to living and our strife and
so many people are striving to live from
a capitalistic materialistic right they
just you can't put that kind of pressure
on the planet right and and what does
that mean and we don't need to okay so
so we need to change what we're valuing
from the capitalist materialistic greed
culture which we have justified for a
whole host of different reasons some of
which natural science in its
self-centered referential control system
as legitimized in an unjustified way
because we're a lot more communal than
Western science would suggest we need to
shift so what I about sort of ok mass
capital took care of the more or less
started to take care of the first levels
of Maslow but the back levels of Maslow
needs serious attention and we need to
come together as serious communities to
cultivate our sense of relational value
in the relational world to cultivate our
embrace of wisdom traditions that enable
self-actualization transcendence
whatever you want to call it but growth
we need to come together and embrace our
existential condition and and have
conversations like this I think about
this this is we get together it didn't
cost us anything you know other than a
zoom it cost us no carbon footprint you
know we get to connect we get to learn
we get to share you know it's what
Socrates wanted I mean he's wandering
around think about what he had to deal
with right I'm in a leather chair
bitching about well guys it's a really
tough time and it's like well actually
everything's fine I'm like I'm biting my
nails can I cope a couple of things to
say to that one is people will they
historically they will take a hit to
their standard of living if they get
some
sense that they're gonna get an increase
in meaning in life people will reliably
do that and I'm wondering if the crisis
the virus crisis makes that now apparent
to people look you're actually taking
significant hammering and again like you
I do not want to be dismissive of people
that are going through significant
economic hardship right now that's a
real thing
it's a real thing and I want to
acknowledge it but right it's the note
you know the realization I suppose that
outside of impoverishing people which we
have to avoid right covering people we
can actually do with so much less if we
right if that actually creates a space
drives us into making more meaning which
is what's happening right now right and
Socrates used to wander into the
marketplace and say look at all the
things I don't need as a way of trying
to exemplify that and of course then
Diogenes took it much much further so I
think that's a that's exactly right in
the sense that you know there's an
opportunity here to realize in the deep
sense of the word you know how that how
much we can reduce the pursuit of the
lower levels of Maslow's hierarchy and
how we can transfer a lot of that effort
into the higher levels I think this is a
real opportunity we have right now of
realizing that's exactly well that's it
that's a wonderful summary of what I
think are the silver is the silver
lining in this if they're you know and
and and that's what I've actually said
you know again not minimizing what
people have to go through but the fact
of the matter is it's actually very well
placed
you know this virus is in many ways
ironically very well-placed to
potentially help us to wake up to how to
reevaluate our value system and start
the processes by which we can live lives
in ways that are much more sustainable
and harmonious with Mother Earth and
things like that yeah I like the the
idea of that it's it's almost like a
rock-bottom realization they can wake
somebody up other
addiction yes yes Jordan actually Jordan
Hall
you know offered that in one of his
frames and one of the things that I saw
and that's exactly you know we're we get
addicted to our materialistic standards
of living and that's what and and then
we would be afraid of change and indeed
now change is coming there's a lot of
reasons that some of us are you know
hell I'm in pretty good spent and I'm
feeling it and I think you're feeling it
too and stress at times right and that's
inevitable that's part of what changes
if we can keep the heads about us if we
can build the kinds of clarity of the
valued outcomes that we have through
this thing on the other side of this
thing I really do believe that you know
five years from now ten years from now
you look back and it's like actually wow
we are are much more coherent were much
more resilient we're much more on a
sustainable path we learned a lot from
that and actually that we're better off
for yeah that's so part of it had to do
with getting the three peas back
together that you pointed to as being
separated from each other you know
reintegrating the psychotherapy with the
pedagogy with the phyleus sophia we have
to come back together again in a really
powerful way if we're going to make a
fundamental transformation in what we
care about and how we care about it
that's exactly right in fact that's
that's really what the passion of the
unified framework and tree theory and
knowledge thing that I built is about is
is although my first focus was on
psychotherapy you know that's what I
encountered the spiritual encounter of
the psychotherapy room and then wanted
to bring the best of but I could to from
all the various perspectives and I sort
of backed into well how do you put all
these things together and then I woke up
to the fragmentation of knowledge
problem you know which you know wake up
to in terms of you know capital C s
cognitive science right it's just
there's a real problem of our language
systems not talking to each other
they're siloed they have anchor points
and but they're really at a macro level
they're really basically pre
paradigmatic in the way they relate to
each other they fragmented in the
profession I make the crap out of us you
know and they certainly they fragment
you and I in the Academy
yeah you know and and and then they
can't translate into society obviously
if you and I have trouble as academics
talking to each other Jesus well you get
that out and the dinner-table kinds of
stuff so if we can yoke if we can build
frameworks realize relevant information
necessary to pull together you know
level philosophy pedagogy the
psychological knowledge that we learn
for the 21st century then we can unify
our knowledge systems in particular way
build practices that are engaging in
that and that's that's an integrated
coherent society there will be a lot
more resilience these constant yeah I
think that's very well said very well
said we have a couple minutes left this
has been fantastic
like really you've been on fire today
thank you for that and thank you for
agreeing to come here and talk with me I
really appreciate it and like I said I
see your particular knowledge and wisdom
have any an important role to play in
all of this I just wanted to give you
you know in the last couple minutes we
have an opportunity to any sort of
summative converging thoughts you want
to express before we become I think the
main thing I would say is I really do
believe that we have sort of a we I it
opportunity meaning how are we going to
relate to it as nature the virus our
institutions
how are we going to relate to ourselves
how are we going to come together I
think the the virus is scary there's a
lot of stacked worries we're probably in
some for some dark clouds but there
really is an opportunity here there's a
really opportunity to connect to learn
how to cope together to confront some
existential realities and to thrive on
the other side of it as a
psychotherapist I've seen that many
times I think there's an opportunity for
a collective trauma but a collective
pose my my mentor master degree lawrence
calhoun was all about post-traumatic
growth right and and how we grow after
trauma so I'll hope for us too
take this blow come together reconstruct
an identity and foster post-traumatic
growth on the other side of it great
thank you so much great so thanks for
having me here I really appreciate the
opportunity